Guide to the National Lawyers Guild Records TAM.191
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Part 2, Series XVI: Audiocassettes, 1981-1995
  - B209-29 Challenging Political Exclusions and Deportations, Jun 1989 (Box 296, Folder 106)
  - B209-30 The Emerging Law of International Labor Rights, Jun 1989 (Box 296, Folder 107)
  - B209-32 Critical Legal Studies and The Guild, Jun 1989 (Box 296, Folder 108)
  - B209-33 Veterans Administration Law, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 109)
  - B209-34 Anti-Racism Work for the Guild, What Should It Be and How Can It Be Sustained?, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 110)
  - B209-35 Developments in Asylum Law, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 111)
  - B209-36 Social Change through Legislation; How Is This Possible?, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 112)
  - B209-38 Trade Union Activity in El Salvador and Guatemala, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 113)
  - B209-39 The Labor Movement's Necessary Role in Disarmament and Conversion to a Peacetime Economy, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 114)
  - B209-40 Constitutional Police Policies and Practices, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 115)
  - B209-41 Texas v. Johnson, The Supreme Court Flag-burning Case, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 116)
  - B209-42 Banquet: Keynote Speaker Frances Moore Lappe, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 117)
  - B209-43A Making Affordable Non-Discriminatory Housing a Right, Getting from There to Here, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 118)
  - B209-43B Making Affordable Non-Discriminatory Housing a Right, Getting from There to Here, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 119)
  - B209-44A Dismantling the Military Industrial Complex, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 120)
  - B209-44B Dismantling the Military Industrial Complex, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 121)
  - B209-45A Plenary: Resolutions, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 122)
  - B209-45B Plenary: Resolutions, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 123)
  - B209-46 China Update, Jun 1989 (Box 297, Folder 124)
  - NLG Annual Convention, Portland, August 9-14, 1995: 01 Keynote Address, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 125)
  - 03 T1 From Law School to Law Collective: Transforming the Legal System, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 126)
  - 03 T2 From Law School to Law Collective: Transforming the Legal System, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 127)
  - 04 Cutting Edge Issues in Cyberspace, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 128)
  - 05 Developments in Political Asylum, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 129)
  - 06 Three Strikes and You're Out, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 130)
  - 06 Three Strikes and You're Out, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 130dup)
  - 09 Case Studies on the Effect of U.S. Intervention in the Caribbean and Latin America, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 131)
  - 09 Case Studies on the Effect of U.S. Intervention in the Caribbean and Latin America, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 131dup)
  - 11 T1 Affirmative Action: Taking Back the Initiative on the Civil Rights Front, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 132)
  - 11 T1 Affirmative Action: Taking Back the Initiative on the Civil Rights Front, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 132dup)
  - 11 T2 Affirmative Action: Taking Back the Initiative on the Civil Rights Front, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 133)
  - 11 T2 Affirmative Action: Taking Back the Initiative on the Civil Rights Front, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 133dup)
  - 12 T1 Creating a New Political Party/Proportional Representation, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 134)
  - 12 T1 Creating a New Political Party/Proportional Representation, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 134dup)
  - 12 T2 Creating a New Political Party/Proportional Representation, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 135)
  - 12 T2 Creating a New Political Party/Proportional Representation, Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 135dup)
  - 14 Revisiting McCarthy (Part 1 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 136)
  - 14 Revisiting McCarthy (Part 1 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 297, Folder 136dup)
  - 15 Revisiting McCarthy (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 137)
  - 15 Revisiting McCarthy (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 137dup)
  - 16 Basic Problems in Police Misconduct Cases (Part 1 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 138)
  - 16 Basic Problems in Police Misconduct Cases (Part 1 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 138dup)
  - 17 Basic Problems in Police Misconduct Cases (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 139)
  - 17 Basic Problems in Police Misconduct Cases (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 139dup)
  - 18 Reinventing Socialism, Theory and Practice (Part 1 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 140)
  - 18 Reinventing Socialism, Theory and Practice (Part 1 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 140dup)
  - 19 Reinventing Socialism, Theory and Practice (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 141)
  - 19 Reinventing Socialism, Theory and Practice (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 141dup)
  - 20 New Immigration Protection for Battered Immigrant Women and Children, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 142)
  - 20 New Immigration Protection for Battered Immigrant Women and Children, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 142dup)
  - 21 Legal Services / Entitlements (Part 1 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 143)
  - 21 Legal Services / Entitlements (Part 1 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 143dup)
  - 22 T1 Legal Services / Entitlements (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 144)
  - 22 T1 Legal Services / Entitlements (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 144dup)
  - 22 T2 Legal Services / Entitlements (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 145)
  - 22 T2 Legal Services / Entitlements (Part 2 of Session), Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 145dup)
  - 23 Issues Related to the Irish Peace Process, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 146)
  - 23 Issues Related to the Irish Peace Process, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 146dup)
  - 24 The Anti-Gay Initiative Epidemic, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 147)
  - 24 The Anti-Gay Initiative Epidemic, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 147dup)
  - 26 Labor, Employment and the ADA, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 148)
  - 26 Labor, Employment and the ADA, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 148dup)
  - 27 The Domestic Face of Militarism, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 149)
  - 27 The Domestic Face of Militarism, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 149dup)
  - 28 Women's Luncheon: Poetry Reading by Pamela Crow; Address by Mililani Trask, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 150)
  - 28 Women's Luncheon: Poetry Reading by Pamela Crow; Address by Mililani Trask, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 150dup)
  - 29 The Origins, Present Work and Future Efforts of the Guild's Defense of Immigrants' Rights and Affirmative Action, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 151)
  - 29 The Origins, Present Work and Future Efforts of the Guild's Defense of Immigrants' Rights and Affirmative Action, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 151dup)
  - 30 T1 Domestic Violence in the Age of O. J. Simpson, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 152)
  - 30 T1 Domestic Violence in the Age of O. J. Simpson, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 152dup)
  - 30 T2 Domestic Violence in the Age of O. J. Simpson, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 153)
  - 30 T2 Domestic Violence in the Age of O. J. Simpson, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 153dup)
  - 31 Chiapas and Beyond: Movements for Social Change in Mexico, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 154)
  - 31 Chiapas and Beyond: Movements for Social Change in Mexico, Aug 1995 (Box 315, Folder 154dup)
  - 32 Litigating in the New Age, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 155)
  - 32 Litigating in the New Age, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 155dup)
  - 33 Immigrants' Rights under Labor Law, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 156)
  - 33 Immigrants' Rights under Labor Law, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 156dup)
  - 34 Disability Law and AIDS Discrimination, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 157)
  - 34 Disability Law and AIDS Discrimination, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 157dup)
  - 35 Domestic Use of Newly Ratified Human Rights Treaties, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 158)
  - 35 Domestic Use of Newly Ratified Human Rights Treaties, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 158dup)
  - 36 Ending Corporate Rule: Citizen Organizing, Democracy and the Legal Profession, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 159)
  - 36 Ending Corporate Rule: Citizen Organizing, Democracy and the Legal Profession, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 159dup)
  - 37 Grassroots Organizing to Block the Right Wing Backlash, Aug 1995 (Box Digitized Access Files, File tamwag_TAM191_ref8008, Box 316, Folder 160)
    Format: Audiocassette, Duration: 86 min.
  - 38 T1 Violence against Women: Fighting Back against the Backlash of the 90's, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 161)
  - 38 T2 Violence against Women: Fighting Back against the Backlash of the 90's, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 162)
  - 39 T1 Contract on America - It Is Class Warfare, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 163)
  - 39 T2 Contract on America - It Is Class Warfare, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 164)
  - 40 T1 Business Plenary, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 165)
  - Opening Night Reception, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 166)
  - T1 International Labor Movement, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 167)
  - T1 International Labor Movement, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 167dup)
  - T2 International Labor Movement, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 168)
  - T2 International Labor Movement, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 168dup)
  - T1 Attacks against People of Color, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 169)
  - T1 Attacks Against People of Color, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 169dup)
  - T2 Attacks Against People of Color, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 170)
  - T2 Attacks Against People of Color, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 170dup)
  - T1 Banquet, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 171)
  - T1 Banquet, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 171dup)
  - T2 Banquet, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 172)
  - T2 Banquet, Aug 1995 (Box 316, Folder 172dup)
- Part 2, Series XVII: Photographs, 1940s-1995
  - Events (Miscellaneous), 1940s-1990s (Box 298, Folder 1)
  - Kersten Committee, 1948 (Box 298, Folder 2)
  - Roosevelt Award Ceremony, 1948 (Box 298, Folder 3)
  - Conference: Orientation, circa 1950s (Box 298, Folder 4)
  - Convention (Chicago), 1959 (Box 298, Folder 5)
  - Columbia University Anti-War Protests, 1968-1969 (Box 298, Folder 6)
  - Conference: Civil Rights (Chicago), 1963 (Box 298, Folder 7)
  - Conference: "Southern Civil Rights Litigation and Northern Lawyers", 1963 (Box 298, Folder 8)
  - Convention (Detroit), 1964 (Box 298, Folder 9)
  - Press Conference (Sheraton Cadillac Hotel), 1964 (Box 298, Folder 10)
  - Detroit Chapter: Annual Dinner (Embassy Hotel), 1965 (Box 298, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Native American Struggles (CONAS), 1966, undated (Box 298, Folder 12)
  - Lecture on Housing (New York University), 1969 (Box 298, Folder 13)
  - NYC Chapter: Dinner, 1982 (Box 298, Folder 14)
  - NYC Chapter: Miscellaneous, 1984-1986 (Box 298, Folder 15)
  - NYC Chapter: Miscellaneous (Negatives), 1984-1986 (Box 298, Folder 16)
  - Convention (Atlanta, GA), 1985 (Box 298, Folder 17)
  - Convention (50th), 1987 (Box 298, Folder 18)
  - NYC Chapter: Dinner, 1987 (Box 298, Folder 19)
  - Convention, 1988 (Box 298, Folder 20)
  - UC Berkeley Student Strike, 1989 (Box 298, Folder 21)
  - Massachusetts Chapter: Miscellaneous, 1992-1995 (Box 298, Folder 22)
  - Free Trade Protests, circa 1993 (Box 298, Folder 23)
  - Haitian Refugees (Guantanamo Bay), 1994 (Box 298, Folder 24)
  - Haitian Asylum Project, 1995 (Box 298, Folder 25)
  - Convention, 1995 (Box 298, Folder 26)
  - Convention (Contact Sheets and Negatives), 1995 (Box 298, Folder 27)
  - Hollywood Ten, undated (Box 299, Folder 1)
  - Membership (Miscellaneous), undated (Box 299, Folder 2)
  - Portraits: Group, undated (Box 299, Folder 3)
  - Portraits: Individual, undated (Box 299, Folder 4)
  - NLG march photo, 1986 (Box 309)
  - NLG Second Annual Convention (Box Shared Tamiment 007, Folder 1)
- Part 2, Series XVIII: Archived Websites, September 2007-ongoing; 11 websites in 11 archived websites.
  This series contains the websites for the National Lawyers Guild, its New York City chapter, and its committees. The websites contain news, press releases, event listings, convention proceedings, internal publications, and governance materials. Many of the websites also include training materials for legal practitioners.
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued semiannually.
  In 2020, https://nipnlg.org/ accruals were increased to biweekly then decreased to monthly in 2021.
  Appraisal
  Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of nlg.org, nlginternational.org, nlg-npap.org, and nationalimmigrationproject.org, nipnlg.org, nlgmltf.org, nlgnyc.org, and nlg-laboremploy-comm.org in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints.
  Crawl was expanded to include Google Documents.
  Facebook was blocked at nlg.org.
  Robots.txt was ignored on nlg-npap.org.
  The series is arranged by crawl date.
  - National Lawyers Guild, September 2007-ongoing
    The National Lawyers Guild (NLG) website holds materials related to Know Your Rights/Risks manuals; Law for the People convention proceedings; the Guild Notes newsletter; the Guild Practitioner journal; the NLG Review; annual reports; referral directories; chapter information; amicus curiae briefs; mass defense briefs; committee information; the legal observer program; fellowships; press releases; news; governance; and their campaigns. Areas focused on by the NLG include the right to protest, international solidarity, prison abolition, labor and employment, legal education, environmental justice, drug policy, and political prisoner release. The website underwent redesigns in circa 2010, 2012, and 2017.
  - National Immigration Project, September 2007-ongoing
    Historical Note
    The National Immigration Project provides assistance and support to legal practitioners, immigrant communities, community-based organizations, and advocates seeking and working to advance the rights of non-United States citizens.
    In 2020, the website redirected from http://www.nationalimmigrationproject.org/ to https://nipnlg.org/.
  - International Committee, September 2007-ongoing
    The National Lawyers Guild International Committee website contains news, information on its subcommittees (Task Force on the Americas, Palestine Subcommittee, Cuba Subcommittee, Indigenous Peoples' Rights Committee, Africa Subcommittee, Haiti Subcommittee, Middle East North Africa Action Group, Human Rights Framework Project, Agent Orange Working Group, Puerto Rico Subcommittee, and Article 9 Working Group), event listings, and publications.
  - National Police Accountability Project, September 2007-ongoing
    National Police Accountability Project is a non-profit membership organization of plaintiff's lawyers, law students and legal workers dedicated to ending law enforcement and detention officer abuse of authority through coordinated legal action, public education, and support for grassroots and victims' organizations combating misconduct.
  - New York City Chapter, September 2007-ongoing
    The National Lawyers Guild New York City Chapter website contains information on their governance; their foundation; the Parole Preparation Project; committees regarding environmental justice, animal rights, mass incarceration, mass defense, labor and employment, immigration, and restorative justice; student chapters; events and news; press releases; job postings; resources and training regarding legal observers and know your rights, and a referral directory. In 2020, the website added a section regarding the George Floyd protests and the Black Lives Matter Civil Litigation Task Force.
  - Military Law Task Force, September 2007-ongoing
    The Military Law Task Force of the National Lawyers Guild website contains their quarterly journal On Watch; information on governance; news on Military Law practice and training, GI rights and counseling, advocacy, analysis, and opinion; press releases; position statements, training and education materials; Military Law library; memoranda on desertion, command influence, individual ready reserves, dissent and whistleblowers, casualty assistance, discharges, and military sexual violence; other publications; book reviews; and convention materials.
    The Military Law Task Force of the National Lawyers Guild is an organization of radical lawyers and legal workers interested in draft, military, and veterans issues.
  - Labor and Employment Committee, December 2011-ongoing
    The Labor and Employment Committee of the National Lawyers Guild is a non-profit unincorporated legal association engaged in legal education and advocacy.
    The Labor and Employment Committee website contains information on their annual meetings and national events in concert with the AFL-CIO Lawyers Coordinating Committee; steering committee members; mentorship program; job postings; press releases; newsletter; resources on economic rights, elections, employment, immigration, injured workers, international issues labor, mass defense, OSHA, wage and hour, and Worker Centers; and projects related to Amicus, Immigrant Workers, International Labor, International Cuba Research, Labor Law Issues, Mass Defense, organizing Labor, Occupational Safety & Health, Section 7 Rights, Solidarity, Voter Protection, Worker Centers, Working America, and other action as needed.
  - Jailhouse Lawyers Handbook, June 2012-ongoing
    The Jailhouse Lawyers Handbook is a resource for incarcerated people who wish to file a federal lawsuit addressing poor conditions in prison or abuse by prison staff. It also contains limited general information about the American legal system. The guide was put together by the National Lawyers Guild and the Center for Constitutional Rights.
  - Mass Incarceration Committee, June 2025-ongoing
    The Mass Incarceration Committee works to "disrupt and abolish carceral systems." The provide support to jailhouse lawyers and political prisoners through letter writing; the monitoring of prison and jail retaliation and neglect; educational programming; rapid response of prison uprisings; and litigation.
    The website contains information on the Old Law Prisoner Project and the Political Prisoner Working Group.
- Part 2, Series XIX: Oral Histories, 1986-2010
  This series contains six oral history interviews recorded on CD-Rs. Three CDs contain an interview with Ralph Shapiro, which was recorded by Michael Nash, head of Tamiment Library in 2010 for an oral history collection on the National Lawyers' Guild (NLG). Other oral histories were conducted by Shapiro and feature NLG lawyers Julius Cohen, Dorothy Shtob, Martin Popper, Bob Silberstein, and Victor Rabinowitz, and were recorded between 1986 and 1988. These interviews were most likely recorded originally on audio cassettes and later transferred to CD in 1994. The interview with Martin Popper cuts short after 20 minutes, likely the result of transfer error from cassette. Original cassettes are not included in this series.
  - Cohen, Julius, 1986 September 18 (Box 311, Cd 1)
  - Popper, Martin, 1986 January 13 (Box 311, Cd 2)
  - Rabinowitz, Victor, 1987 April 30 (Box 311, Cd 3)
  - Shapiro, Ralph, 2010 December 16 (Box 311, Cd 4-6)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Personal family content on the first 25 minutes of disc 1 are restricted until December 2021.
  - Shtob, Dorothy, 1987 April 29 (Box 311, Cd 7)
  - Silberstein, Bob, 1988 January 21 (Box 311, Cd 8)